Traditional DNS tells a workload where a service is.
It does not decide whether that workload should reach it.
Name-Based Secure Routing adds identity, policy,
and short-lived authorization to that route.
A client proves its workload identity to the NBSR control plane.
The control plane asks an OPA default-deny policy.
The control plane alone holds the private ticket-signing key.
When allowed, it creates a short-lived Ed25519 routing ticket.
The verifier receives only the public key. Envoy uses external authorization
and a fixed allowlisted route to the private payments service.
The client cannot connect to that backend directly.
All five Docker Compose services are ready.
The allowed workload resolves payments.internal
and reaches the service through Envoy.
The denied identity receives no route.
An unknown service is also denied by default.
A missing ticket is rejected.
Changing real decoded signature bytes is also rejected.
An automated regression test protects the tamper case.
The ticket cannot escalate its method or path.
The client cannot connect directly to the payments backend,
proving real network isolation.
The short-lived ticket expires and is rejected.
All eight real mandatory scenarios pass.
Tickets bind workload, service, method, path,
gateway audience, and expiration.
Envoy fails closed. Clients cannot choose an upstream,
and the backend has no published port.
Humans directed the concept, architecture, security requirements,
technology, scope, fail-closed criteria, testing, and submission decisions.
GPT-5.6 and Codex accelerated the FastAPI services, OPA and Envoy integration,
Docker and Kubernetes resources, tests, documentation, live validation,
and correction of the Base64 URL tamper-test flaw.
Compose was validated live. Kubernetes resources passed
offline validation, but live kind was not tested.
This is a validated prototype, not intended for production,
and it does not replace DNS. Identity and policy decide the temporary route.
The public repository is available on GitHub.